# NAVEEN N RAVICHANDRASEKARAN

250 East 6th Street, Apt 0402 \$\infty\$ Saint Paul, MN 55101

(832) · 720 · 2393 ♦ http://www.naveenravichandrasekaran.com/ ♦ nravi.research@gmail.com

#### **SUMMARY**

Professional Software Engineer with experience in the general areas of parallel and distributed computing. Specifically, my technical skills focus on the following areas: (i) parallel programming models and runtime systems (MPI and Partitioned Global Address Space models like OpenSHMEM, Global Arrays, and Coarray Fortran); (ii) parallel computing architectures (Cray Supercomputers and Clusters, multi-core systems, GPUs and Intel MIC), and (iii) high-speed interconnect libraries(DMAPP)

#### **EDUCATION**

# University of Houston, Main Campus

December 2015

M.S. in Computer Science - Specialization in Parallel & Distributed Systems

Anna University, India

May 2011

Bachelors in Engineering - Electrical & Electronics Engineering

#### **EXPERIENCE**

Cray, Inc

12/26/2015 - Present

Software Engineer - Programming Environment Message Passing Toolkit

Saint Paul, MN

- · Software Enhancements and Parallel Optimizations for Cray Supercomputer and Cluster environments
- · Work specifically on Cray software stacks like Cray MPI, Cray SHMEM, and Global Arrays
- · HPC and parallel programming runtime optimizations for Cray hardware to be utilized by specific customers like U.S government and commercial petroleum industries
- · Participate and represent Cray in OpenSHMEM standards committee

Cray, Inc

05/18/2015 - 12/25/2015

Intern - Programming Environment Message Passing Toolkit

Saint Paul, MN

- · Research, Prototype, and Implement new features in Cray SHMEM programming library
- · Optimize Global Arrays library for NAMD and NWChem Chemistry applications

#### University of Houston

09/14/2013 - 05/15/2015

Research Assistant - HPC Tools

Houston, TX

- · Research Assistant to Dr.Barbara Chapman(Chair, Computer Science & Mathematics(CSM) Group Brookhaven National Laboratory)
- · Research and explore strategies for runtime optimizations, and compiler-tools interactions for large-scale parallel systems using OpenSHMEM and Coarray Fortran programming models

## Cognizant Technology Solutions

06/23/2011 - 07/12/2013

Programmer Analyst

Chennai, India

· Design parallel test framework to validate bank statements for a leading financial services company

#### TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Computer Languages
Parallel Programming Models
Network Libraries
Architectures

C/C++, Fortran, Java, Python, Ruby, Scala OpenSHMEM, OpenMP, MPI, Coarray Fortran DMAPP, Verbs, Libfabrics

Cray Supercomputers, & Clusters, Intel MIC

## **Current Projects**

#### 1. Cray SHMEM

- optimize and maintain Cray SHMEM for different platforms
- implement new features as per the OpenSHMEM standards
- propose and prototype new features like Communication Contexts, Symmetric Memory Partitions and Teams(PE-Subsets)

## 2. Cray MPICH

• create an optimized message matching layer for the MPI implementation.

# 3. Cray Global Arrays(Cray-GA)

• optimize and maintain the ComEx - DMAPP communication layer

#### Past Projects

## 1. OpenSHMEM Reference Implementation

**Project description:** University of Houston worked with *Oak Ridge National Laboratory* to standardize OpenSHMEM via a community-driven specification with a reference implementation. **My contributions:** I have been particularly involved in the optimization of the collective communication performance.

# 2. Coarray Fortran

**Project description:** Coarray Fortran is a set of new language features incorporated into the Fortran 2008 standard which enable parallel programming in Fortran with minimal changes to the language syntax. It is a joint project between University of Houston and *Total* **My contributions:** I am particularly involved in the optimization of the Coarray Fortran runtime library with new underlying communication layers.

### REFEREED CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS

- 1. N.Namashivayam, B.Cernohous, K.Kandalla, D.Pou, J.Robichaux, J.Dinan, and M.Pagel. "Symmetric Memory Partitions in OpenSHMEM: A case study with Intel KNL". In Proceedings of Fourth Workshop on OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies: Big Compute and Big Data Convergence, August, 2017, Annapolis, Maryland, USA.

  To Appear
- K.Kandalla, P.Mendygral, N.Radcliffe, B.Cernohous, N.Namashivayam, K.McMahon, C.Sadlo and M.Pagel "Current State of the Cray MPT Software Stacks on the Cray XC Series Supercomputers". In proceedings of Cray User Group Meeting, 2017, Redmond, Washington, USA. To Appear
- 3. N.Namashivayam, D.Knaak, B.Cernohous, N.Radcliffe, and M.Pagel. "An Evaluation of Thread-Safe and Contexts-Domains Features in Cray SHMEM". In Proceedings of Third Workshop on OpenSHMEM and Related Technologies: Enhancing OpenSHMEM for Hybrid Environments, August, 2016, Hanover, Maryland, USA.
  - https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-50995-2\_11
- 4. N.Namashivayam. "OpenSHMEM as an Effective Communication Layer for PGAS Models". Master's Thesis, University of Houston, October, 2015.
  - https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/1c6b/9787b0eda7723a14ba6bc92cd77a7dcb0102.pdf

- 5. N.Namashivayam, D.Eachempati, D.Khaldi and B.Chapman. "OpenSHMEM as a Portable Communication Layer for PGAS Models A Case Study with Coarray Fortran". In Proceedings of IEEE Cluster 2015, September, 2015, Chicago, USA. https://www.computer.org/csdl/proceedings/cluster/2015/6598/00/6598a438.pdf
- N.Namashivayam, D.Khaldi, D.Eachempati and B.Chapman. "Extending the Strided Communication Interface in OpenSHMEM". In Proceedings of Second OpenSHMEM Workshop: Experiences, Implementations and Tools, August, 2015, Annapolis, Maryland, USA. https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-26428-8\_1
- 7. D.Knaak, and N.Namashivayam. "Proposing OpenSHMEM Extensions Towards a Future for Hybrid Programming and Heterogeneous Computing", In Proceedings of Second OpenSHMEM Workshop: Experiences, Implementations and Tools, August, 2015, Annapolis, Maryland, USA. https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2952638
- 8. N.Namashivayam, S.Ghosh, D.Khaldi, D.Eachempati, and B.Chapman. "Native Mode-Based Optimizations of Remote Memory Accesses in OpenSHMEM for Intel Xeon Phi", 8th International Conference on Partitioned Global Address Space Programming Models (PGAS 2014). https://dl.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=2676881

## KEY ACTIVITIES

1. OpenSHMEM standardization Effort, Participate and represent Cray Inc. in OpenSHMEM standards committee. http://openshmem.org/

## AWARDS AND ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- 1. Best Paper Award, 8th International Conference on Partitioned Global Address Space Programming Model(PGAS 2014).
- 2. Graduate Assistant Tution Fellowship, September 2013 May 2015.
- 3. Best Undergraduate Student Project, Mepco Schlenk Engineering College, Anna University, India, 2011.